hello and welcome everyone it is October
12th
2023 and we are in the final lecture
session six in physics' information
processing with Chris Fields so Chris
thank you for this journey exciting to
get to this final lecture which will be
followed only by the the last discussion
for this go around so it's really
awesome and to you for this
lecture uh thank you Daniel and uh
welcome everyone to this uh last session
that I'll be doing uh with a focus on
biology and just to give A Brief Review
as as usual uh We've focused in this
course on generic Quantum systems uh by
which I mean just any Quantum
system uh that has some number of
degrees of freedom and we really haven't
made any assumptions about these systems
other than the assumption that both
interacting Partners have sufficient
degrees of
freedom that um they can be considered
separable uh so their boundary is small
with respect to the total size of each
of the inter interacting
systems and I want to emphasize again
that that the approach we've taken is
completely topological so we haven't
assumed anything about embedding in
space um and as we've characterized
these systems we focused really on two
things uh one the N the amount of
information that the two systems can
exchange and that amount is determined
by the size of their boundary it's
determined by this number in which is
the Hilbert space dimension of the
boundary and as we've discussed now in
several of the sessions we can think of
this boundary as a collection of in
cubits via which the two systems A and B
communicate the other
uh feature of the interaction on which
we
focused um is the reference frames that
are used by the two systems to interact
with this set of cubits and it's these
reference frames that
assign the information that flows
between A and B uh meaning or functional
significance or actionability
or however you want to uh refer to
the idea that uh when a system gets some
information it does something useful
with
it so those are very generic kinds of
ways of characterizing an interaction uh
you can think of it as a qualitative
characterization the the semantics of
the information and a quantitative
characterization the amount of
information but other than that we've
left the the nature of these systems
open and this characterization allowed
us to reformulate the free energy
principle in uh Quantum information
theoretic terms as the principle that
interacting systems behave in a way that
will asymptotically align their
reference
frames and we saw
that full alignment of reference frames
uh is equivalent to
entanglement so the interact the the FP
drives systems toward entanglement which
is not surprising because that's uh what
happens to generic Quantum systems they
may start out separable but if they
interact long enough they'll become
entangled so we've had a discussion that
is really very uh
generic now we showed a couple of
sessions ago that under these very
generic
assumptions we got some interesting
outcomes and one is that if systems have
sufficient degrees of
freedom uh under the action of the
Fe they will be driven toward making um
a diverse set of measurements of their
environment because they're trying to
get information about it so that they
can predict what it's going to
do and that as they add ways of making
measurements they'll come up against our
non-commutativity of their
measurements and this may be due to
Intrinsic mathematical facts about their
measurements and it may just be due to
their limited supply of free
energy so I'll either way what this
induces is
compartmentalization and uh the
requirement for internal classical
communication on internal
boundaries so I just wanted to to
reemphasize that this is a result of
basic physics and we see
compartmentalization of course
ubiquitously in
biology um but this suggests to us that
uh features of
biology that are very
familiar actually follow from from
Fairly deep
physics and compartmentalization is one
of
them we then talked last time about
space and time and the computational
requirements of on any system that is
able to perceive an external clock or
perceive an external spatial
layout and we discussed this these uh
from a from a very kind of Developmental
Psychology point of view uh we discussed
it using essentially the kinds of terms
on the right here as opposed to uh the
kind of language that's much more
Technical and mathematical that's used
in physics to uh derive SpaceTime as
emergent from information
transactions but we at least hypo HTH
esize that both of these are ways of
getting to the same sense of emergent
SpaceTime and one important outcome of
this discussion was that systems can
perceive external
clocks so external periodic Behavior
with fewer computational resources so
before they're able to perceive spatial
layouts and we'll get back to this
later so organisms and maybe other
complex systems seem to
manage um a collection of uh
capabilities that are all mutually
dependent so um memory depends on having
layouts of persistent things that can be
distinguished uh so it depends on space
and it certainly depends on
time
um space gives structure to persistent
objects memory allows you to identify
persistent
objects and objects in turn give
structure to space by being located in
different
places and objects enable the
fundamental
uh requirement for memory which is some
form error correction so that one has
enough
redundancy in the memory to check to see
whether a memory has been
degraded so
organisms um seem to manage uh a
physically very important process which
is the use of
SpaceTime and memory as a basis for
cognition uh you'll recognize these four
functions that are that are mutually
interdependent as underlying complex
cognition across the board and you can't
really do complex cognition unless you
have these
capabilities so today we're going to put
some of these things together in a
discussion of
biology and and in by looking forward to
Future directions not just in biology
but in all of quantum information
Theory so let's talk about biological
systems living systems uh which of
course includes us uh but also includes
all other organisms and communities of
organisms and so forth at multiple
scales and I want to put forward a
fairly um radical
hypothesis that living systems are just
just generic Quantum systems that the Fe
has driven to a high level of
computational
complexity so what does this belief
say it suggests that living systems are
just Quantum
systems that have enough degrees of
freedom and a sufficiently
complicated internal
dynamics that the Fe by requiring them
to predict what their environment is
going to do
next has driven them to make complicated
measurements and complicated inferences
on the basis of those measurements that
enable fairly complicated actions on the
environment so these are systems that
you would characterize as computers
essentially information processing
systems with a high degree of
computational
capability now this is is clearly uh as
much a philosophical hypothesis as an
empirical hypotheses and uh that's due
in part to the fact that we don't really
have a good definition of what a living
system is we can just point and say you
know that's a living system and that
thing over there isn't uh but beyond
that we don't have much of a theory and
of course people have worked on a theory
of what is life for decades
um but there's not a lot of
agreement and
so this is uh a in a sense a
definitional kind of hypothesis and we
test such kinds of hypotheses by seeing
if they're useful conceptually to help
us understand what living systems are
doing now soon as we as we put forward
something like this inevitably the
question comes up are living systems
really Quantum systems or are they
classical in some intrinsic
sense and this question is really an
artifact of of two things one the
continuing association between Quantum
systems and microscopic systems uh which
is of course traditional quantum theory
was developed to deal with microscopic
phenomena it was first
tested uh as a theory of microscopic
phenomena and it's only in the past
couple of decades that quantum theory is
being applied to big things uh to
cosmology for
example so uh there's there's a long
tradition of association
between Quantum and microscopic and
living systems are
mesoscopic
um much bigger than atoms bigger than
molecules so and they're not nearly as
big as cosmological systems so they're
somewhere in between and those systems
have traditionally been regarded as
classical and even chemistry even
biochemistry is still taught in a very
classical way so we're not used to
thinking of these things as Quantum
systems but at least in the approach
we've taken in this course um all
physical systems are quantum systems and
classical information exists only on
boundaries only on boundaries between
systems and it only describes their
interaction and I want to emphasize I
mean know I've said it before but since
this is the last class I want to say it
again that this is not a universally
held
view um it's it's a view that's becoming
more
common um and I think a generation from
now it will probably be the D dominant
view of things uh but it's it's not fair
to say that it's the dominant view now
it's it's I think quite fair to say that
it's a view on the rise especially in
the quantum information and quantum
gravity
communities but from a strict empirical
perspective uh we know a number of
things uh we know that accurate
molecular Dynamics calculations require
quantum theory
uh we know that a lot of uh biologically
important molecular
processes uh use quantum coherence we
know that things like hydrogen bonding
can only be
understood uh using quantum
theory uh we know that cellular free
energy budgets are way too small to
support fully classical information
processing if we think of information
processing in terms of what proteins are
doing or what other molecules are doing
in terms of changing
shape know we know that shape changes in
in proteins and other molecules underly
all cellular information processing so
if we think of them as actually
implementing cellular information
processing we have way more information
processing than could be funded
classically and finally we know that
human cognition exhibits contextuality
so human cognition uses Quantum
coherence it's not a classically a
classical causal process in all
cases but this is still a very nent
field and it's a field with a lot of
potential and I think again a generation
from now uh Quantum biology is going to
be regarded as a very mainstream
Endeavor uh even though it's something
of a a small emerging field
now and I'll just show you one picture
uh in support of this third
Point um these are this is a plot of uh
measured uh free energy usage converted
to numbers of bits processed at one
kilohertz for a number of of procaryotic
and eukaryotic cells uh all that I could
find a few years ago that had good uh
calom metric measurements versus the log
of their area their uh membrane surface
area and the thing to note here is that
these cells are processing classical
information at pretty low rates
kilohertz to gigahertz rates for a
thousand bits at a
time and we know that a lot more is
happening uh in cells than that now
cells have many more than a thousand
proteins
and those proteins are all moving all
the time and if that motion is
processing information then there's not
nearly enough uh classical not nearly
enough thermodynamic power to to power
all of that information
processing so let's now talk a little
bit about life and living
systems and uh what they look like
now here's a view of living systems from
the point of view of genome diversity
this is a few years old so it's out of
date by now but it tells us a lot
qualitatively uh it tells us that almost
all genome diversity is
microbial that the sorts of organisms
that we're familiar with mediumsized
organisms like us animals and plants
have only a tiny amount of genome
diversity so we think of ourselves as
pretty diverse we think of ourselves as
as quite different from other animals
from flies or worms
or sponges or something like that but in
fact we're not all that different from
them we we share many many proteins with
all of those other organisms we share
the same cellular organization and so
forth we're not in fact all that
different from plants
and uh we're we're much more similar to
the fungi than to the
plants
so we get a very biased view of genome
diversity when we just look at familiar
large types of living
systems uh most genome diversity is is
buried down there in the microbial
world this isn't the only way we can
look at life uh as a diverse set of
organisms we can also look at it in
terms of a cell
lineage uh the fact that we're all
related at the DNA level tells us that
we're all descendants of a common
ancestor which is usually called Luca
the last Universal common
ancestor and uh Luca is generally
modeled as being a cell uh more or less
like a bacterial cell so fairly simp
simple uh with not very many Pathways uh
with maybe a DNA genome and if Luca
didn't have one then they
arose fairly shortly thereafter because
all organisms that we know of have DNA
genomes but the point of looking at Life
as a
lineage is that we get a diagram that
looks very much like the cell lineage in
from an embryological situation
much like the cell lineage of of our own
bodies growing from a fertilized
egg and in particular looking at Life as
a lineage shows us that not only do we
share DNA with all other organisms we
actually share a membrane cytoplasm
that's continuous in time all the way
back to Luca and so continuous in time
between us and and
bacteria so if you look at life this way
you realize that that life is in a sense
all one organism all one connected
structure that's developed over time
through division cell
division and so we are very closely
related uh to all other parts of life in
the same way that different cells and
our bodies are closely related to each
other the time span just longer I mean
here the time spans three and a half or
four billion years uh between us and and
Luca these lineages have been diverging
for that long but they're still
continuous and in particular uh they
form a continuous cell
membrane so when you think of life in
this way we realize that we are
reasoning from just one example when we
think about terrestrial life and this
strongly limits what we can say about
living systems what we can say about
biology that we really only have one
example the the lineage that descends
from Luca here on Earth and at some
point we may have more examples and
there's certainly groups working on
artificial organisms that aren't part of
this lineage that are constructed from
Parts derived from this lineage but
aren't members of this lineage
themselves and that may tell us
something new about
life but if we if we think of life this
way um we see something very
important which is that as life grows
its boundary gets
bigger and
since the boundary of a system
constitutes its informational
environment uh its Dimension getting
bigger means that more information flows
into it from its environment and more
information flows out of it into its
environment so as as life develops from
Luca it gets a larger and larger
informational environment and this
Convention of its boundary grows and
grows now what that means if you go back
to our original picture of two
interacting
systems is that the number of the
dimensionality of the physical
environment is
decreasing uh and we think of the
physical environment as increasing in
size we have the expanding universe and
all that but what's increasing in size
is
space and if space is emergent
then that increase is not a real
increase in degrees of freedom what
we're really interested in is the
Hilbert space of the physical
environment as distinct from the Hilbert
space of
life and as life gets bigger it it
literally quite literally eats the
physical environment and turns it into
more life so there's less physical
environment
around so the trajectory of life is
toward a bigger information AAL
environment and a smaller physical
environment and as the physical
environment gets smaller you might
imagine it gets easier to predict as the
informational environment gets bigger
you have more information with which to
predict the behavior of the physical
environment so this all hangs together
very nicely with the free energy
principle here's another picture of this
same thing um if we start with some
boundary here on the left lab B around
some system labeled s and it's embedded
in an environment
e then as as s makes copies of
itself um through some process like cell
division then it starts to fill up more
of e it's it's actually converting
degrees of freedom of e into degrees of
freedom of its copies that it's made of
itself and if we think of some larger
boundary drawn somewhere in E here on
the right side I've avbl that b
Prime what happens is that b Prime gets
slowly filled up with copies of s and it
starts to look like a large
organism and that's what life is doing
in the physical environment it's making
a bigger boundary for itself at the
expansive degrees of freedom of its
physical environment
so we can ask what drives this process
uh why is life doing this why is it
making copies of
itself and the answer to that question
at least one answer to that question is
the free energy principle drives it to
do
this and uh I'll just show you some
simulations uh from several years
ago of a cell population uh in this
upper left panel the the green cells are
stem cells that
divide and they've been eded in an
environment that's safe on the left side
and 100% lethal on the right side so
this they're embedded in it in an
environment that's that's conducive to
life on one side and very dangerous as
you get toward the
middle and the purpose of these um
simulations was to study what
happens when the stem cells are able to
divide and create not just other stem
cells but create specialized progeny
that don't divide so sematic
progyny U that don't divide and hence
have free energy resources thermodynamic
resources that they can devote to doing
something other than dividing
cell division is incredibly expensive
when it comes to energy so if you take
that energy and apply it not to cell
division but to protecting the stem
cells um you can allow the stem cell
population to expand and that's what
these other simulations show the blue
cells are sematic cells that have very
varying ability to protect the stem
cells and if they're fairly good at
protection and they're fairly hard to
kill uh down in the the right bottom
quadrant um you can actually get a
population expanding well into the
highly lethal part of the
environment
so this shows you the Fe in
action uh what the stem cells are doing
is constructing a very predictable
neighborhood around themselves in the
environment by dividing to make progyny
that don't themselves divide that just
um sit there and and help Pro protect
the stem cells so the stem cells are now
living in a safer more predictable
environment and that allows them to
invade more and more of the of their
physical environment by having this
fairly benign informational environment
so this is the FP in action driving the
expansion of Life at the expense of the
physical
environment so that lets us um go back
to this question that was raised last
time about the
mechanism of these scale transitions
that we see ubiquitously in life uh life
gets bigger and
bigger um as time goes on F genetically
and as time goes on
developmentally uh we start with some
molecular
Pathways that somehow get assembled into
a cell that's the origin of Life
question how does that
happen
and about two billion years later cells
start to group together to make
multicellular
organisms now bacteria group together to
make facultative multicellular systems
like microbial Maps three billion years
ago very very early on uh but we don't
see the emergence of obligate multis
cellulars until much much later uh
before the Cambrian explosion but still
less than a billion years
ago and from there things get more
complicated very quickly so uh one has
large multi cellular organisms uh they
develop complicated social
relations that probably first emerged uh
with social
insects uh but are certainly
welldeveloped in in vertebrates
including in
mammals
um organisms uh group together uh in
very complex
ecosystems and um recall here that it's
now known that all multicellular
organisms have obligate microbial
symbiance so all of our bodies are in
fact very complex ecosystems populated
by many many different species of
bacteria and that's true not just for us
but for trees and insects and worms and
sponges and everything
else so
um organism
from a from a body point of view are
themselves ecosystems and
organisms organize themselves into
ecosystems and these ecosystems come
into contact uh across the entire
biosphere so um process is as simple as
the wind uh disperse organisms as small
as
bacteria all over the
planet so
this scaling of Life toward larger and
larger organizational
structures is in a sense the major thing
for biology to
explain and the hypothesis that we
floated last time was that this um
transition from very small scales to
very large scales uses the same
mechanism over and over again or a a
mechanism that has the same structure
over and over
again so the the renormalization group
is is Trivial basically it's this it's
just the identity operating at different
scales or mapping from one scale to the
next so the question is can we can we
approach this in any way uh does this
make
sense and to to try to make sense of it
um we can go to the the one real
developed theory that we have in
biology which uh has been formulated by
Dawkins and others as universal
Darwinism uh this is just kind of an
abstraction of the the modern
synthesis uh between darwinian evolution
and
genetics but Universal Darwinism is
incredibly simple it it's and very
obvious it says if you have systems and
they can copy each other they can copy
themselves and the copies can
diversify then if you want to know
what's going to happen at the population
level uh what you will find is the
systems that copy themselves and
diversify most efficiently will win
because there'll be more of them so they
end up dominating the
population and uh winning gets called
natural
selection but natural selection is not
an extra part of the darwinian process
it's just the outcome of efficiency of
the systems that copy themselves most
efficiently coming to dominate uh any
population so there's no sort of um kind
of hand of God or whatever reaching down
and selecting some organisms and not
others and of course when Darwin put the
idea of natural selection together he
was he was thinking very explicitly of
the analogy of of a gardener or a farmer
uh selecting the the crops or the
animals or whatever that that the
gardener liked best and keeping those
and that's where this selection metaphor
comes from but there's no real process
of
selection in uh evolution by natural
selection it's just copying and
diversifying but this clearly is just
the outline of what a real mechanistic
Theory would be because we need to to
have a story about what copying is and
what diversifying is and what
efficiently
means um and in particular to address
the question that we raised a couple of
slides ago we need to know whether these
mechanisms are the same or at least
isomorph morphic of the same
form at different
scales so um that's what I want to talk
about for the next little
bit let's start with
copying
um up until the
70s copying in biology really meant DNA
replication
and to some extent cell division but the
focus in evolutionary theory was on DNA
replication and in the
70s uh it was
realized that whole genes could be
duplicated so whole genes could be
copied and then shortly uh after that it
was realized that particularly in
procaryotes where genes
functionally related genes are next to
each other in chromosomes often in what
are called
operons that operons could be duplicated
and so entire Pathways could be
duplicated and as genomes began to be
sequenced and structures of genomes were
understood it became clear that genomes
could be
copied
and uh of course we have two copies in
each of our cells with the exception of
red blood
cells of our complete
genome but some plants for example have
six or eight or even more copies of
their genome in each of their cells so
there's large scale genome
duplication uh cell division is clonal
duplication of cells organismal
reproduction works by cell division in
all known
systems um
colonies or societies of organisms
reproduce themselves in part through
cultural
transmission and entire niches reproduce
themselves uh for example in processes
like
um Forest Evolution or desertification
or even
urbanization uh we see humans
reproducing the same sorts of niches in
city after City for
example so these forms of
copying um have the kind of hierarchical
dependencies that one might expect so to
duplicate Pathways you have to duplicate
genes uh to duplicate cells you have to
duplicate The
genome to duplicate organisms you have
to duplicate
cells and this suggests that this
copying operation is indeed scale free
that that each each level the copying
operation at each level enables the
copying operation at the next
level now with diversification we see
much the same
thing
um in the early days of of the modern
synthesis and and still in the work of
people like like Richard
Dawkins diversification is is generally
thought of as random so mutation for
example is thought of as
random and um here I have Barbara Mento
who is kind of the hero of
non-randomness in um doggedly over
decades pointing out that much of genome
diversification is not random at all and
[Music]
um that genomes actively diversify by
moving whole clusters of genes
around and uh duplicating them or just
changing their positions so that they're
under the influence of different local
uh
control so at the Gene and genome level
uh you have active
diversification by various processes uh
entic processes or as as Mento showed us
transpose on mediated mechanisms which
are enzymatic at the at the
bottom um cells actively diversify by
lots of different
mechanisms and uh in the
70s uh Carl W
was in part large personally responsible
for pointing out that in the microbial
world there's a lot
of Gene transfer and uh again no one
believed him for quite a oil but now
it's it's broadly accepted that microbes
exchange DNA uh very frequently and
across large distances
phenetically and this is how things like
microbial resistance to antibiotics
spread so quickly or one one way that it
spreads so
quickly and it's a tremendous um agent
of of essentially speciation to the
extent that that even makes any sense in
the microbial
world of course in our cells we have
functional
differentiation
uh as mentioned earlier there are lots
of symbiotic
interactions that lead to
diversification in cells by radically
altering their local
environments and of course sex is a is a
mechanism for
diversification uh organisms actively
diversify in many different ways the
most obvious one is just by moving
around by moving to a different
environment uh the organism is exposed
to different inputs and is allowed
different
outputs and so it can it can move into a
different direction U morphologically
genetically
Etc uh organisms can regulate their own
evolvability by altering things like DNA
repair systems or activating
transposons again these are sorts of
things that
uh went very much Against the Grain when
they were first discovered but are now
pretty well
accepted and of course organisms can
learn and so can diversify their
behavior by diversifying their
computational
capabilities uh and social groups of
course actively diversify uh in many
different
ways and
uh organisms are increasingly non-human
organisms are increasingly regarded as
having cultures that they pass on
intergenerationally by intergenerational
learning and can exchange with with
other
groups so
diversification uh is active and occurs
at every
scale and again diversity Al although
this is a bit less clear than in the
case of of
coping uh diversification mechanisms at
one scale enable diversification
mechanisms at other
scales so for example uh transpose on
mediated mechanisms uh enable horizontal
Gene transfer in in
microorganisms and e
f tells us that efficiency is actually
about
intelligence because the FP drives
systems to build good models of their
environments or the behavior of their
environments and what a good model lets
a system do is reach a single goal by
many different means because it allows
in a sense
planning um and it allows flexibility
and adaptability
and I put William James here on this
slide because he was the first as far as
I know to Define intelligence as this
ability to use different means to reach
the same
goal now in evolution that's that's long
been
known and it's called convergent
evolution when you see two
lineages adapting to a single
environment with very different genetics
and very different morphologies
and uh often the organisms will end up
with similar morphologies that work well
in that environment but very different
genetics and very different
biochemistry so throughout Evolution we
see this phenomenon of functional
convergence balancing structural
Divergence at many many different levels
so we have multiple genes for very
similar
proteins we have multiple pathway ways
that do more or less the same
thing uh we have different cell types
that support the same basic
functions uh we have tissues that have
that are are fairly different uh but
that have the same functions for example
eyes and different kinds of organisms
that allow Vision but have very
different structure and of course we
have functional convergence and social
relations and if we look at how cells in
interact um traditional evolutionary
theory really focuses on
competition but we now know that cells
cooperate that they exchange resources
in various
ways uh even across vast differences in
in philogyny for example The Interchange
between plants and fungi or between
bacteria and
us um we know that cells in a sense
persuade each other by uh secreting
things like hormones that cause other
cells to do different
things um cells deceive each other uh
for example microbes that are trying to
escape the immune
system uh and cells coers each other
cells even kill each other when they uh
detect for example genetic
defects so these sorts of of Social and
economic and even political uh ideas are
useful for describing living
systems from the level of cells on up I
mean they were developed in Social
settings uh to describe what goes on in
human societies and then extended to
other
animals and now it's very clear that
they extend to individual cells so when
we think about social
intelligence we can think about social
in elligence even at the level of
individual
cells and we see these sorts of of
competition cooperation resource
exchange Etc even at the level of
microbial Mass so biological structures
that are three billion years
old now of course intelligence is
necessary but it's not sufficient for
being selected it won't protect you
from impacts of of asteroids that happen
to land in your planet
uh which has happened often in the
evolution of the earth and we're now
trying to figure out how to predict and
and prevent such
things uh but it's you know who knows
whe whether we'll be successful with
that uh but and
this
intelligence is necessary when it's
viewed in this Fe sort of way
intelligence is what lets you build
models that um enable you to predict the
environment so where does this leave
us um by thinking of evolutionary theory
in terms of scale-free
mechanisms we seem to have a picture in
which we start with Quantum systems with
a certain level of
complexity and the FP actually gives us
scale-free biology or something very
close to scale-free
biology and that's very interesting
because the FP of course is a generic
principle it just says that systems do
what they need to do to keep
existing and this way of thinking gives
us some
predictions uh one is that we'll find
compartmentalized problem solving
everywhere uh because the FP drives
compartmentalization and uh the reason
is just non-commutativity of of
measurement
processes it predicts that we'll see
hierarchical organization everywhere uh
in the same way we did on that first
compartmentalization slide where once
you have a number of compartments you
need a meta compartment that if nothing
else distributes free energy so some
sort of very basic attention system and
we see attention systems of course
throughout
biology um it predicts that living
systems will have very limited classical
data
structures so since they have to write
classical data on their
boundaries uh and their boundaries are
much smaller than they are then they'll
and because writing classical data is
expensive that living systems will tend
to use as little classical data as they
can get away
with since classical data is needed for
thermodynamic irreversibility
where we see thermodynamic
irreversibility uh that's where we look
for classical
data uh we saw that organisms will be
able to detect time first uh before they
can detect space so we can expect
organisms to uh have
clocks before even before they can uh
represent space and of course we see
things like dial variation throughout
biology and finally the the FP predicts
this ASM totic collapse of separability
back to
entanglement so it predicts that our
living systems will eventually degrade
and become indistinguishable from their
environments and we know that happens at
the cell level and the individual
organism level uh you know we call it
death
so the Fe seems to give us a lot of the
features of biology and it gives us
these features in a scale-free way and
it deres them from this very basic
physics so where does that leave
us I think it leaves us here with a with
a
challenge not just to thinking about the
Fe which is what this course has been
about but to to Quantum information
theory in
general and and that challenge is to
evolve from the kind of conceptual and
theoretical
utility that we've been discussing in
this course and which is is very welld
developed in the physics
Community to of some sorts of empirical
and technological
utility and I've listed three areas here
where qit is very active uh one in Quant
gravity and
cosmology and you're probably familiar
with things like string theory that sort
of Fairly famously seem not to be
empirically
testable and the quantum gravity
Community is enormous uh many thousands
of people working in this area but
coming up with theories that can be
tested
empirically uh at the scales that we can
actually do experiments so at accessible
energy scales for example has proved to
be very
difficult um so this is a real challenge
to the field is somehow uh getting not
just to empirical testability but to
some sort of technological
utility and you can imagine that if the
the main prediction
of quantum gravity is that SpaceTime is
emergent that
um there could be enorm utility in
that uh some ability to manipulate the
way SpaceTime
emerges the second area of course is is
quantum information and Computing and
here massive resources are being put
into uh technological
utility and I think it's reasonable to
expect that we'll have useful quantum
computers within a generation at any
rate so there I think the the field is
going quite well and the last area what
we've talked about here is quantum
biochemistry and biology and this I
think is an area with enormous practice
uh
promise that um maybe some of you will
actually contribute to uh making this
area more useful
technologically and more accessible
empirically but at least we have a
picture of how these different areas
together so uh that's it thank you very
much for participating in this class uh
Andrew will be
doing your questions sorry um could you
just repeat the last like 30 seconds
from anderw will
be
Chris will be last discussion session on
Saturday the 28th of October at the
usual time 8 AM Pacific time and the
interactive Q&A is open I really
appreciate your questions I try to
answer them
uh and thank you very
much awesome can I ask a question or do
you want to call it
here sure go ahead all
right inks wrote Chris spoke last time
introducing the mechanisms of scale
transition
um I'll read your question then I'll fix
the cropping on the live stream Chris
spoke last time introducing the
mechanisms of scale transition of these
essentially semantic theories about how
one scale embeds in another scale I
would love to learn more about this
especially in terms of natural language
semantics and human cognition semantics
versus machine
learning wow well that's that's a very
good
question
um I think that's a very relevant
question given uh the sorts of machine
luring that we see deployed in uh
systems like chat
GPT and especially as these
systems start to associate language with
images for
example and as as such systems are
embedded in
uh robotic systems that can actually
move around in the world and interact
with real
objects I think one of the one of the
key questions in natural language
semantics is to what extent does it
depend on reference uh to what
extent
do the meanings we attach to
words um or the
usages that we uh allow for Words depend
on our ability to connect words to to
external
objects and to what extent uh do those
abilities uh rely on connections between
words themselves so if you think of of
an llm like chat GPT by itself it's just
a statistical model of relationships
between words as used in some Corpus of
text which is large of course but uh we
can debate its
representativeness and so that's a model
of uh semantics
that's entirely self-contained it's
entirely relations between different
pieces of
language whereas when we start to
connect those words statistics to images
or better yet to actual
objects that are interacted with uh not
just visually but haptically for example
by a robot they start to be connected to
external
reference and that transition I think is
going to be very very interesting to
watch and it's just starting so we all
have ringside
seats on an incredible experiment in
semantics and
um
so so that would be my response really
to that question is is keep your eyes on
this
experiment and see how it goes because
it's bound to tell us something
about uh how semantics really
works and I suspect that there will be
enormous opportunity to start relating
the results of that experiment to uh
what we see in in developmental
psychology for
example wow awesome all right Tucker
asks
areas of macroscopic quantum mediated
phenomena in biology that get Chris
Fields
excited
um I think the one that excites me the
most right now is just this question
of how cells are managing to do the
information processing that they're
doing and
um how much of
it they can
accomplish
or I think the right way to put it is
how can they get away with so little
classical
information and um I don't think we have
the cell biology yet to answer that
question but I think asking the question
may help us designed the right kinds of
Cell Biology to look for an
answer and our cell biology has been
organized around the
idea that the structures that we see are
essentially static that they're
classical and that they're constructed
in a way that's thermodynamically
irreversible but if we think of what we
measure as not necessarily reflecting a
static structure
uh I think we'll start to uh
conceptualize it differently and build
models of it differently I mean clearly
when we look at things like uh protein
structure we're looking at snapshots of
something that's very
Dynamic and when we look in a a
chemistry textbook and we see you know
pictures of this confirmation that
changes to that confirmation we think of
those as static stable structures that's
kind of a switch uh
but it's not actually a a switch the way
a light switch is it's a much more
Dynamic
process and the kinds of molecular
Dynamic simulations that allow you to
study that process are incredibly
complicated and and time expensive and
and uncertain uh due to resolution
problems and and other things but
uh I think thinking of these as
as kind of fluid reversible
processes um is going to change the way
we think about
them that's a great point and it reminds
me of the more physics based way of
thinking about the paths that could
happen between observations or the
statistics based way of samples of a
dynamical process and in biology we know
that even if we take a snapshot okay
this organism is 1 centimeter today it's
2 centimeters tomorrow something changed
so we know there was a developmental
process then we know there's an
ecological process and then there's an
evolutionary context Eco
evoo and then from that more biological
understanding of contextual
developing
organisms all of these different
biological phenomena
actually help us expand our space of
measurement and
Analysis for material that on one hand
some people may have called inanimate
but then they
have their own Dynamics different time
scales and so bringing some of
those like the challenges of measuring
and observing intervening in historical
and
biological things gives us a bigger
understanding even on measuring and
summarizing
analyzing ensembles or scales that that
don't immediately appear to have that
kind of
uh but in one sense they clearly
are and uh to the extent that we can
think of these structures that are much
larger than we are
individually as living systems cognitive
systems Etc I think we'll understand
their Dynamics
better okay final question upcycle Club
wrote How can a Quantum system detect
and respond to Quantum context shifts
switches which are changes in the
measurement basis or the entanglement
structure of the
[Music]
system
um well
uh the an the answer here is is simple
and not very informative it's by making
measurements which is all that Quantum
systems can actually
do and um making measurements that
follow probing
actions that uh try to push the
boundaries of the model of a
context
uh you know when when having this
discussion I I always like to go back to
the frame problem in artificial
intelligence which is the
problem
um formulated in the late 60s
of predicting what what won't change is
the result of an action so it's sort of
the inverse of the problem of predicting
the side
effects and if you can predict all of
the side effects You can predict what
doesn't change so it's equivalent to the
the question of predicting all the side
effects and context change is a side
effect and it's often in
[Music]
unobserved and maybe unobservable side
effect
but if you have a model that says I'm
working in this
context then you can intentionally probe
the boundaries of that
model and see if you can actually alter
the context you're in as a way of
discovering what context you're in and
know humans do that in Social settings
all the
time
um but I I I I think this is something
that we need to uh to think about
happening at many different scales I
suspect that cells are doing this all
the time we just don't know
how there's so much to say there it just
makes me think of the the Paradox or the
tension between expecting the expected
expecting the unexpected and life
needing to expect both of
that right
so thank you Chris it's been an amazing
lecture series many people in the live
chat are very appreciative and and um
we'll look forward to their submitted
questions and their participation in the
final discussion coming soon so thank
you Chris till next time okay and thank
you all bye
ciao